# **Tatiana Fokina**

**Accessibility Engineer** 

Tbilisi, Georgia +9 000 000 000 <u>fokinatatian@gmail.com</u> <u>linkedin.com/in/tanya-fokina</u> <u>fokina-dev.ru</u> UK Global Talent Visa Holder

CPACC-certified Accessibility Engineer with 5+ years of Web/Frontend Development, specializing in developing user-centred interfaces.

Demonstrated proficiency in web technologies, including HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. Mastery of WAI-ARIA, WCAG, and ATAG standards and guidelines. Experienced with assistive technologies and testing tools.

Leadership in accessibility advocacy through public writing, speaking engagements and community initiatives.

## **Work Experience**

**Doka Guide** August 2022 – Present, remote

Editor, accessibility engineer, contributor.

- Architected a content plan, directed and launched the Accessibility section within a 3-month timeframe.
- Collaborated with 70+ contributors to develop 20+ articles on accessibility, 20+ materials on HTML and CSS, and 50+ on other web technologies.
- Crafted more than 100 articles on topics such as accessibility, HTML, and CSS.
- Executed a WCAG-EM-based accessibility audit, resolving 29 issues on the project's website.

**JUG Ru Group** May 2019 – June 2020, St. Petersburg, Russia Frontend developer.

- Led accessibility audits on 10+ conference sites, improving Lighthouse accessibility scores by 48%.
- Maintained and modernized 10+ legacy projects, enhancing performance by 15% and ensuring functionality for 5,000+ users.
- Engineered 4 features for user accounts on the ticket platform in collaboration with designers, frontend, and backend developers, enhancing user experience and functionality.
- Co-developed a live streaming conference platform from concept to launch within a 2-month timespan.

**Self-employment** December 2016 – May 2019, St. Petersburg, Russia Freelance web developer.

- Conceptualized and implemented 7 landing pages and 3 multi-page sites for clients, strengthening their online presence.
- Developed 3 templates for MODX and Drupal, simplifying client content management processes.
- Remediated 5 websites to comply with government accessibility standards, reducing legal risks.

#### **Skills**

Core technologies. HTML5, JavaScript (ECMAScript 6), CSS3.

Advanced skills. TypeScript, Angular, Next.js, Sass/SCSS, Stylus, Pug, Nunjucks.

**Standards and legislation.** WAI-ARIA 1.2, WCAG 2.2, ATAG 2.0, WCAG-EM 1.0, Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), Section 508, Equality Act 2010, EN 301 549, Web Accessibility Directive (WAD), European Accessibility Act (EAA).

Assistive technologies. NVDA, JAWS, VoiceOver, TalkBack, Microsoft Magnifier, ZoomText.

**Tools and platforms.** Git, GitHub, GitLab, axe DevTools, Wave Evaluation Tool (WAVE), Accessibility Insights, Pa11y, accessibility bookmarklets, Storybook, 11ty, Gulp, Figma.

#### **Education**

**St. Petersburg State Institute of Culture** June 2015, St. Petersburg, Russia Specialist's degree in Integrated Library Systems (ILS).

### **Certificates, Community Involvement**

**Courses and certificates.** Practical Accessibility course, <u>CPACC</u>, Trusted Tester (v5.1.3).

**Community experience.** Google's Women Techmakers ambassador (WTM); host <u>Inclusive</u> <u>Pineapple</u> podcast; organizer of <u>pitera11y meetup</u> and Doka Guide meetup.

**Publications and talks.** Translation of <u>Accessibility Myths project</u>; post <u>Understanding Skip Links</u> on professional blog; article <u>What Are ARIA Live Regions</u> on Doka Guide; talk <u>Accessibility and Typography</u> at Tbilisi A11y & UX Day.